Guide to the Helen Morton Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Helen Morton Papers
1932-1991
RG 133
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(11 boxes)
These papers document the later part of Helen Morton's career, particularly her work with the University Christian Movement in New England. Born to a privileged New England family in 1898, Helen Morton spent her long life engaged in ecumenical religious and social work with a variety of U.S. and international organizations.
Morton, Helen
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Biographical / Historical
Helen Morton was born June 5, 1898, and grew up in Newton, Massachusetts, spending summers at the family home on Yarmouth Island, Maine. After graduating from Vassar College she received a Master of Science degree from the Simmons College School of Social Work in 1923 and was involved in settlement work in Boston and internationally. From 1933 to 1940 Morton was executive secretary of the National Student Council of the YWCA, a position in which she traveled widely and was involved in interracial activities. In 1935 she took on the added assignment of co-executive of the new National Intercollegiate Christian Council and was elected a member of the World Student Christian Federation Executive Committee. Following a trip to Asia in connection with the WSCFin 1940, Morton became general secretary of the Cambridge (MA) YWCA, but with the coming of the Second World War, she returned to work with the World Student Christian Federation. For six months during 1946 Morton was a staff member of CIMADE (ComitÉ Intermouvement Aide aux EvacuÉs) in France and then, until 1948, served the World YWCA in Geneva. In 1949 she returned to Boston to become the Associate Headworkder of South End House. She remained in Boston until 1980 except for two years overseas with the World Council of Churches; she served as parish assistant and "lay reader" of St. Stephen's Church and was involved in urban renewal work in Boston. Morton served on the Board of the University Christian Movement of New England and these papers were received in connection with the UCM archives, YDSL Record Group No. 88.
Scope and Contents
The papers in this record group were received with the archives of the University Christian Movement in New England and primarily relate to Helen Morton's involvement with student Christian work during the late 1960s through the early 1980s. They complement various other collections at the Yale Divinity Library that document student Christian work in the U.S. and abroad.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1969-1984
II. Notes, 1969-1990
III. Collected Material, 1967-1991
IV. Collected Publications, 1932-1981
College students -- Religious life; Ecumenical movement; Morton, Helen; University Christian Movement in New England; World Student Christian Federation
- Correspondence, 1969-1984; Series I
  - A, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alle, Ann Silver, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B, 1969-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bazoche, Placide, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bloy, Myron, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - C, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Campbell, Fay, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Carroll, Bishop Edward, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clough, Len, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Colvin, Harold, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cook, Frank, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cox, Harvey, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - D, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - E, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Espy, R.H. Edwin, 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - F, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Flory, Margaret, 1969-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - G, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Grant, Fern Babcock, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - H, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - I, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - J, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - K, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Kitchen, Wilmer, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - L, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lerrigo, Edith, 1975-1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Limbert, Paul, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lovett, Sidney, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - M, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mackie, Robert Cuthbert, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Mains, Francis Helen, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - McLean, Milton, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - McMichael, Jack, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Moon, Carrol, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - N, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - O, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - P, 1969-1976 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Pfuetze, Paul, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Price, Earnest, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - R, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Roy, Andrew, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - S, 1969-1977 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Schwieso, Chuck, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Seamans, Henry W, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Stewart, Colonel George, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - T, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Thompson, Hugo, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Tucker, Luther, 1969-1984 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Turnbull, Helen, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - V, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Visser 't Hooft, W.A., 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - W, 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Y, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Z, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Christmas Circulars, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Excerpts from various correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Miscellaneous Circulars, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Morton's Circulars to "Network of Senior Friends", 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Notes, 1969-1990; Series II
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1969-1978 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - OT Notes, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - OT Notes, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 61-67)
  - UCM Notes, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 68)
- Collected Material, 1967-1991; Series III
  - Organizations
    - Association for the Coordination of University Religious Affairs, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Canadian SCM, 1971-1979 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - National Ecumenical Student Conference, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - SCM: Blue Ridge Assembly / Seminar Notebook, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 72-74)
    - SCM: Blue Ridge Assembly "Specials", 1976 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - SCM: Morton's Circulars, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - SCM: Perspective, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - SCM: Staff-Clergy Ecumenical Conference, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - UCM, 1968-1991 (Box 4, Folder 79-88)
    - UMHE, 1975-1980 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - WCC, 1967-1975 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - WSCF: Africa, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - WSCF: Asia, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - WSCF: Christian Unity, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - WSCF: Education, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - WSCF: Executive Committee, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - WSCF: General Assembly, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - WSCF: General Assembly in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - WSCF: General Assembly in Sri Lanka, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - WSCF: General Assembly in San Francisco, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 99-100)
    - WSCF: General Secretary Risto Lehtonen, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - WSCF: Mailing Lists, 1969-1974 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - WSCF: Miscellaneous, 1969-1982 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - WSCF: Morton's Circulars, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - WSCF: New Headquarters, 1969-1975 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - WSCF: Philip Maury Contributors, 1965-1969 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - WSCF: Philip Maury Fund, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Policy for publications, 1976-1981 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Seventy Fifth Anniversary Fund, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - US Committee meeting, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - World University Service, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - YMCA/YWCA, 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Topical
    - California SCM, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - Episcopal Church, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Feminism, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - Filipino People, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Literacy, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - MA: Lowell, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - MA: Springfield, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 119-120)
    - MA: Worcester, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - Miscellaneous Material, 1973-1977 (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - New World Foundation, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 123)
    - Women's Film Co-op, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 124)
    - University of Maine and Orono Community, 1971-1975 (Box 7, Folder 125)
    - Valley Women's Center, 1972-1976 (Box 7, Folder 126)
    - Women's Movement in Worcester, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 127-128)
    - Women's Movement in Springfield, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 129)
- Collected Publications, 1932-1981; Series IV
  - WSCF
    - Dossier, 1973-1978 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - Europe Report, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - Federation News, 1956-1962 (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - Journal, 1978-1981 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Life and Mission of the Church, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 134)
    - Miscellaneous Publications, 1962-1979 (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - New Folk Hymnal, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 136)
    - Newsletter, 1971-1978 (Box 9, Folder 137-138)
    - Student World, 1945-1950 (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - Other
    - Collected Pamphlets, 1932, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 140)
    - For the People, 1970-1974 (Box 10, Folder 141)
    - Information Services, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 142)
    - MA Publications, 1970-1972 (Box 10, Folder 143)
    - Miscellaneous Articles, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 144)
    - RISK, 1969-1975 (Box 10, Folder 145-146)
    - Yankee Student Opinion, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 147)
    - Worship in Ecumenical Movement, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 148)